because tlb is kind of like a cache
let's talk about how it is organized in
terms of cache properties
first
is it direct map or fully associative or
somewhere in between well it is small so
it is already very fast so it tends to
be fully or highly associative
usually we don't have direct map tlbs
because that would sacrifice the hit
rate for speed but because it's so small
it's already very fast so we don't
really need that
how about the tlb size
we want it to hit at least as often as
our cache so we wanted to cover more
memory than the cache
so we usually want our tlb to be
somewhere about 64 to 512 entries
what if we need more tlb entries in
order to get the hit rate that we want
well you don't want it to be too large
because then it's gonna become slow
in that case you want to have a two
level tlb the first level or at level
one tlb will be the small and fast one
that hits in a single cycle but if you
have a miss there we have a larger level
two tlb
it has a hit time that is several cycles
so it's significantly slower than l1 but
still way faster than going through
memory and doing the translation
and it is large it can be several
thousand entries because
with several thousand entries we can
still support relatively good hit times
but not a single cycle time